<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call to humiliation for the grievous sin of persecution in two sermons, preached at the publick fasts in Lemster, in the county of Hereford, Wednesday May 21 and June 18, 1690 / by William Woodward ...</title>
            <author>Woodward, William, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12764999</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12764999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93566</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67020)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93566)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call to humiliation for the grievous sin of persecution in two sermons, preached at the publick fasts in Lemster, in the county of Hereford, Wednesday May 21 and June 18, 1690 / by William Woodward ...</title>
                  <author>Woodward, William, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93566:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93566:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A <hi>Call to Humiliation</hi> For the Grievous SIN OF Perſecution, In Two Sermons, Preached at the Publick Faſts in <hi>Lemſter,</hi> in the County of <hi>Hereford, Wedneſday May</hi> 21. and <hi>June</hi> 18. 1690. By <hi>William Woodward</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gal. 4. 16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Am I therefore become your Enemy, becauſe I tell you the Truth?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel.</hi> 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93566:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93566:2"/>
            <head>TO Edward Littleton Esq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN we were called upon by Authority to National Faſting and Humiliation, I thought it my Duty to look into the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> expecting to find a Full and Humble Confeſſion of all the <hi>Piacula,</hi> and Great Provocations of the Land, and in that Black Catalogue the <hi>Grievous Sin</hi> of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> the rather becauſe one of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who is thought to have Aſſiſted in Compoſing thoſe Forms, had told us in a <hi>Preface</hi> Publiſhed ſome years ſince, <q rend="inline">That it may be reaſonably apprehended, that it may have contributed not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to fill up the Meaſures of the Sins of a Church, and to bring down ſevere ſtrokes—again, <hi>they</hi> who had let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves looſe to all the Rages of a Mad Proſecution of ſome Poor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet and Deluded People—ought ſeriouſly to Profeſs their <hi>Repentance</hi> of this Fury in Inſtances, that may be as Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Edifying, as their Rage has been Publick and Deſtructive.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But that <hi>Bloody Sin,</hi> I perceived upon ſearch, had eſcaped the Notice of our Eccleſiaſtical Guides, ſo that all our Fines, Flights, Impriſonments, and Cruel <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage from our Fathers and Brethren for almoſt Thirty Years, was to go for nothing; whereupon I Reſolved to call over ſome of our Laws, which had been Drawn up againſt the Nonconformiſts and Proteſtant Diſſenters, that I might be able to give better ſatisfaction to my ſelf, and to thoſe alſo that ſit under my Miniſtry, that though the Lord be Juſt and Righteous in all the ſorrow we have known, yet Man was not ſo, whilſt we were <hi>Scourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Scorpions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſome, who it may be are ſtill too much in Love with Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, have been Offended with what I have done, and miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it, makes this publication the more Neceſſary, for if we are
<pb facs="tcp:93566:3"/> called to Mourn for <hi>National</hi> Sins, 'tis fit we ſhould <hi>know</hi> them, that we may with all poſſible Fervor, entreat the Lord of his Rich Grace and Mercy, to Deliver us from thoſe Judgments, which are wont to purſue theſe Guilts.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>We have known days of great Tribulation upon the Account of Religion, in the Heat of them the Moor, the Place which your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mother <hi>Adorns</hi> as well as <hi>Inhabits,</hi> was Patmos to me; <hi>there</hi> the Saints Aſſembled, <hi>there</hi> we ſaw the Primitive Times, <hi>there</hi> we had our <hi>Antelucanos Coventus,</hi> the Doors being ſhut for fear of the Jews, <hi>there</hi> we remembred our Friend in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and in your Return we have ſeen the Return of our Prayers.</p>
                  <p>It calls for Songs and <hi>Davids</hi> Harp to ſee you come home Crown'd with that which is infinitely better than the Treaſure of the Eaſt, though with that too; when many others in exchange of Religion left behind, bring thence nothing but <hi>Apes and Peacocks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Lord who can do good againſt evil, hath brought back our Captivity, and enlarged the Curtains of his Tabernacle among us, we can meet at <hi>Ornan</hi>'s Houſe, and ſit with ſafety as well as delight, under the ſhadow of the Tree of Life; you have not been afraid, nor aſhamed to appear in the place of our Solemnities, and a grateful remembrance we retain of your endeared kindneſs.</p>
                  <p>At your feet, Sir, I ſet down theſe Papers, which if they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, as I think they are, I am ſure you have both Integrity and Courage to own them; I know you to be one of thoſe that <hi>wiſh for the Godly Diſcipline of the Primitive Church,</hi> and would have it <hi>reſtored,</hi> that the Lord Jeſus may reign with more glory among us, to whoſe Grace both you, and all yours are recommended by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>June <hi>26th.</hi> 1690.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Humble Servant, <hi>William Woodward.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93566:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luke 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</bibl> 
                  <hi>But Jeſus, turning unto them, ſaid, Daughters of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves, and for your Children.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AFter <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> had pronounced Sentence of Death againſt our Lord, he was led forth to Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> the place of his Crucifixion; 'tis ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>there followed him a great company of people, and of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which alſo bewailed and lamented him.</hi> Our Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as the Great High-Prieſt, was now about to offer up upon the Croſs that Great Sacrifice, which was to take away the ſin of the World; and it was meet to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the preſence of all the people. This was <hi>Dies Cippurim,</hi> the great Day of Expiation and Atonement, in which our <hi>Jubile</hi> began. <hi>A great multitude of people followed him.</hi> In which there might be ſome prefiguration too, that notwithſtanding all the malice and oppoſition of the World, the Amazing Love of Chriſt, in dying for ſinners, would in all Ages draw multitudes after him. <hi>When I am lifted up from the Earth, ſaith our Lord, I will draw all men unto me, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying by what death he ſhould die,</hi> John 12. 32, 33. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>As</hi> Moſes <hi>lifted up the Serpent in the Wilderneſs, even ſo muſt the Son of Man be lifted up.</hi> The <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was his <hi>Type,</hi> which healed all bitten of Serpents, that looked up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93566:4"/> it. The means was not <hi>likely,</hi> but weak and deſpicable, for what could a <hi>Serpent of Braſs do?</hi> Why not rather a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of Gold? The Serpent of Braſs was Gods Ordinance, and by his Bleſſing healed, whiles the <hi>Golden Calves</hi> of Mans Invention bring both a ſnare and a curſe. There were alſo <hi>ſundry Women which bewailed and lamented him,</hi> either as an <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, excellent perſon,</hi> unjuſtly condemned to die, or elſe from a Principle of Divine Faith and Love, knowing, that their ſins made his Croſs heavy, for their ſakes he was <hi>numbred with Tranſgreſſors,</hi> and was now going to lay down his Life upon the <hi>Mountain of Myrrh, and Hill of Frankincenſe.</hi> Our Lord, it ſeems, heard the voice of their weeping, (O let him hear the voice of <hi>England</hi>'s weeping this day) and turning to them ſaid, <hi>Daughters of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves, and for your Children,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which notes <hi>bitter weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> with all the outward Expreſſions of inward trouble of Heart; <hi>Weep not for me, O ye Daughters of</hi> Jeruſalem, who am now going to triumph upon the Croſs, as well as to die; <hi>but weep for your ſelves, and for your Children,</hi> becauſe of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite miſeries, which will ſuddenly break in both upon <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and <hi>the Land of Judea.</hi> Thoſe ſore Judgments of Sword and Famine are coming to you upon the Wings of the Wind, this Generation ſhall not paſs away e're <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was once the <hi>City of God,</hi> the <hi>Excellency of Beauty,</hi> the <hi>Crowned City,</hi> and <hi>Joy of the whole Earth,</hi> ſhall be made a hiſſing, and an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to all the Countreys round about, <hi>weep for your ſelves, and for your Children,</hi> for the days are coming in which the <hi>burren Womb</hi> and <hi>dry Breaſts</hi> ſhall be accounted Bleſſings; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the tender and delicate Women had never been Mothers, than through want and Famine to eat their Children of a ſpan long. When a <hi>Papiſt</hi> came to <hi>Biſhop Hooper</hi> at the Stake, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the Fire, with a pretence of compaſſion, ſaying, Sir, <hi>I am ſorry to ſee you thus,</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> replied, and haply in allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to this of our Lord, <hi>Be ſorry for thy-ſelf, man, and lament thy own wickedneſs, for I am well, I thank God, and Death to me for Chriſts ſake, is welcome.</hi> Weep for your ſelves and your Children. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was now become like the Cities of the Nations, like that Heatheniſh <hi>City of</hi> Nineveh, <hi>Civitas ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93566:4"/> a Bloody City, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3. 1. in her was found the Blood of all the Lords Prophets and Righteous Servants, the Blood of the Son of God, and Saviour of the World, whence 'tis that ſhe is compared unto a <hi>dry Tree,</hi> Luke 23. 31. as being fitted for that Fire, which the Juſtice of God would ſhortly kindle in it by the <hi>Roman Legions.</hi> From the words we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Saints preſent Sufferings deſerve not Tears in compariſon of the future ſufferings of cruel Perſecutors;</hi> there is no proportion between a Drop and an Ocean, a Moment and Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thoſe that have Bowels of Compaſſion ſhould mourn upon the proſpect they have of the miſeries which will follow a National Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and Perſecution of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the opening of this point we ſhall conſider theſe <hi>five things.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>When</hi> Perſecution is <hi>National.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The Law leſſens not</hi> the <hi>Guilt of Perſecution.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Perſecution brings ſore Judgments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Perſecution</hi> calls for <hi>Mourning.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Perſecution of the</hi> Truth <hi>proceeds from the Natural Enmity of Man againſt the Light of Truth and Holineſs,</hi> which ſerves only to vex the Conſcience when it doth not renew the Heart. The <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> were Burning and Shining Lights, ſhining in Holineſs, burning with Zeal; thundering in their Doctrine, lightning in their Life. The <hi>Two Witneſſes in their Sackcloth tormented them that dwelt on the Earth,</hi> Revel. 11. 3, 10. the Divine Light ſhining through their Sackcloth offended the tender Eyes of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World: The Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> tormented <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> who vowed his Death, yet was he taken up to Heaven in peace with a peculiar mark of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 11. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> tormented Inceſtuous <hi>Herod</hi> by naming his <hi>Herodias,</hi> Mat. 14. 3, 10, 11. 'Tis Death to touch the ſore place of Great Perſons, either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Two Witneſſes,</hi> who were <hi>Oyl and Light,</hi> Revel. 11. 4. were bold to ſay the <hi>Pope</hi> was <hi>Antichriſt, Rome</hi> was <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Religion there was Superſtition and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93566:5"/> Idolatry, it gave ſuch vexation to the Followers of the Beaſt, that they could not reſt nor be merry till they ſaw their dead Bodies lye in the Streets of the Great City, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 7, 8, 10. Cain <hi>who was of the wicked one, ſlew his Brother; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſlew he him? becauſe his own Works were evil, and his Brothers righteous,</hi> 1 John 3. 12. The <hi>Targum on Geneſis</hi> ſays, wicked <hi>Cain</hi> denied the Providence of God, and the Judgment to come, and becauſe <hi>righteous Abel</hi> aſſerted both, therefore his Brother ſlew him. <hi>Cain is dead,</hi> ſays <hi>Bucheltzerus,</hi> he is dead, but he lives ſtill in his Heirs and Executors. <hi>Qui clavam ejus ſanguine Abelis rubentem circumferunt.</hi> Who carry about with them as a Holy Relique <hi>Cain</hi>'s <hi>Bloody Club.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the Truth may be ſaid to be <hi>National,</hi> when it hath wrought it ſelf into the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land:</hi> And indeed Perſecution is never ſo brisk and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as when it hath the Law on its ſide: It hath ever been the wiſdom of thoſe, that erect <hi>Golden</hi> Images for Worſhip in the Plain of <hi>Dura,</hi> that is in their <hi>Generation,</hi> to procure a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree from <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in favour of them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 1, 7. there is ſuch a thing as <hi>framing miſchief by a Law,</hi> Pſal. 94. 20, 21. They were Jews, that ſaid, <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to die,</hi> John 19. 7. and when once a <hi>Law</hi> is paſſed, <hi>they gather themſelves together againſt the Soul of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and condemn the Innocent Blood.</hi> The Followers of the Lamb become Criminals, and the beſt of Men are <hi>made offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for a word.</hi> This, the Holy Ghoſt calls <hi>weighing the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the hands,</hi> Pſal. 58. 2. Juſtice is wont to be repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us with a <hi>Ballance</hi> in her Hand, and <hi>Palas</hi> (in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew)</hi> ſignifies not only to <hi>weigh,</hi> but to frame any thing by <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Line,</hi> ſo that the expreſſion of <hi>weighing the violence of the hands,</hi> notes profound exquiſite Malice and Oppreſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretence of preciſe and accurate Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>The Thrones of Juſtice whiles Thrones of Ivory,</hi> 1 King. 10. 18. pure and white are honourable, but if they degenerate, and become <hi>Thorns of Iniquity,</hi> they are no longer under the care and regard of God, but are an abomination to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> by the Craft and Arts of Bad men, gain the Countenance of the <hi>Law,</hi> that <hi>doth not Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93566:5"/> the <hi>Guilt,</hi> but Aggravate it. When <hi>Pilate</hi> boaſted of his power over our Lord, as tho it were within the compaſs of his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> either to Crucifie, or Releaſe him, <hi>Jeſus anſwered, Thou couldſt have no power at all againſt me, Except it were given thee from above, therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the Greater Sin, John</hi> 19, 10. 11. Hence it apears, that Magiſtracy and Government is Gods Ordinance; <hi>The powers that be are ordained of God, Rom.</hi> 13. 1. for the defence of the Innocent, and the <hi>terrour of evil doers,</hi> ver. 3. and though man, exalted on high, preſumes to do his pleaſure, making his <hi>Will</hi> the meaſure of Juſtice, yet is he accountable to God, who never cloaths any perſon with ſo abſolute and unlimited Authority, as to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the Guilty, and condemn the Juſt. It gives a crimſon and ſcarlet dye to the wickedneſs of Perſecutors, when they ſerve their Malice upon Gods Ordinance, and make the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Covering for their Oppreſſion, therefore ſaith our Lord, <hi>He that delivered me unto thee, hath the greater Sin: He,</hi> that is, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> the <hi>Sanedrim,</hi> or the people of the Jews, <hi>have the greater Sin. Jezebel</hi> makes uſe of the Kings name and Seal, not without the Formality of the Law, and a <hi>Faſt</hi> too, to take away the vineyard and Life of <hi>Naboth,</hi> but her Judgment and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did not ſlumber, notwithſtanding her Complement, for of this <hi>Jezebel</hi> the Lord ſpake, <hi>The Dogs ſhall eat Jezebel by the Wall of Jezreel,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 23. this painted Queen is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> as tho ſhe ſtill Lived and Reigned in the Churches, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. 20, 21. <hi>Thou ſuffereſt that woman Jezebel, which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs to teach and ſeduce my Servants to commit Fornication, and to eat things Sacrificed unto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, and I gave her ſpace to Repent, and ſhe Repented not,</hi> ver. 22. <hi>Behold, I will caſt her into a Bed, and them that commit adultery with her into Great Tribulation, except they Repent of their deeds.</hi> ver. 23. <hi>and I will kill her children with Death, and all the churches ſhall know, that I am he that ſearcheth the reins and hearts, and I will give unto every one of you according to your works.</hi> It was a great blemiſh in the church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> to retain ſo much hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our for this <hi>Jezebel,</hi> by whom it's likely ſome <hi>Naboth</hi>'s ſuffered, though we might find the Prophets of the Lord in the name of <hi>Naboth;</hi> yet we ſhall content our ſelves to obſerve that every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93566:6"/> man as well as <hi>Naboth</hi> hath a <hi>vineyard,</hi> which is <hi>the Inheritance of his Fathers.</hi> The poſſeſſion of a good Conſcience, and they muſt not part with it to humor King <hi>Ahab,</hi> but muſt rather run all hazards, and fall a ſacrifice to this wicked <hi>Jezebel,</hi> who, when ſhe can with her Painted Beauty, ſteal away the hearts of Princes, will get the ſtamp of the <hi>Royal Authority,</hi> upon her bloody Contrivances, and deſtroy every <hi>Naboth,</hi> as a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of God and the King, becauſe he will not alienate the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his Fathers, nor ſuffer his <hi>Vineyard</hi> to be <hi>Converted</hi> into a Garden of bitter <hi>Herbs,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 2. Magiſtrates are ſaid to be <hi>Shields,</hi> rather than <hi>Swords, Pſal.</hi> 47. 9. their office is the Defence of Vertue and Holineſs, 'tis an accurſed piece of Sacriledge to take down the <hi>Golden Shields</hi> of the Temple, and beat them into <hi>Swords,</hi> and then conſign them to the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> or to take the ſacred <hi>Horns of the Altar</hi> of the Lord, and adorn the <hi>Head of the Beaſt</hi> with them that with a better Grace he may Gore the Saints, to the Joy of the whole earth, or to entertain the <hi>Levites,</hi> who are <hi>Joyned</hi> to the Lord by a <hi>Covenant of Salt,</hi> with poiſoned wine in the <hi>Golden Bowls of the Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the Truth, though gilded with thoſe great Names of <hi>Law, Juſtice, Publick Safety,</hi> are always acompanyed with terrible Judgments. The Sin is very dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and provoking, other Sins affront the <hi>Deity,</hi> but Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brings to mind that of <hi>Caeſar, Miles faciem feri,</hi> it ſmites God upon the face, it wounds him in the <hi>Apple of his eye, Zech.</hi> 2 8. When <hi>Paul</hi> was mad againſt the Church like the <hi>ravening Wolf of the Evenings,</hi> for he was of the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin, Gen.</hi> 49. 27. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 5. our Saviour call'd to him out of Heaven, and bid him hold, for he ſet all his wounds a bleeding afreſh <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 4. There was a curſe, which fell upon the earth by the Sin of <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3. 17. and man multiplyeth the curſe upon himſelf by his Implacable Enmity againſt the <hi>ſeed of God:</hi> whiles the <hi>Jews</hi> were the <hi>Segulla,</hi> the peculiar Treaſure of of the Lord, all ſorts of <hi>Plagues,</hi> did light upon the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and the nations round about, for oppreſſing them; but when the <hi>Jews</hi> became <hi>Loammi,</hi> and ceaſed to be the people of God, all ſorts of Plagues befel themſelves, becauſe they perſecuted their <hi>Little Siſter,</hi> the anointed of the Lord. Where Chriſt apears
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93566:6"/> in any of his Poor Followers, there is ſome Signature of his Kingly Spirit upon them, which the envious Spirit of man, not being able to endure, ſeeks to extinguiſh, that <hi>the Inheritance may be his;</hi> The Antichriſtian State and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is ſet forth by <hi>Babylon</hi> for her Idolatry; by <hi>Sodom,</hi> for her fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and Immoralities; by <hi>Egypt,</hi> for her oppreſſion and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, is under this condemnation, that the time ſhall come; that there ſhall no more be heard in her, the <hi>voice of the Bridegroom, and the Bride,</hi> Rev. 18. 23.</p>
            <p>1. There ſhall be no more of that cruel and bloody race; The <hi>Inquiſition</hi> hath made <hi>Spain</hi> poor, and the <hi>Dragoons</hi> have made <hi>France</hi> weak; Oppreſſion and Perſecution have broken in pieces all the four Famous Empires of the World, ſet forth in <hi>Daniel, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 32 by the <hi>Head of fine Gold, Arms and Breaſts of Silver, Belly and Thighs of Braſs, Legs of Iron, and Feet part of Iron and part of Clay,</hi> The Empires of the <hi>Aſſyrians, Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſiane, Grecians,</hi> and <hi>Romans.</hi> 'Twas no contemptible counſel which <hi>Tertullian</hi> gave <hi>Scapula</hi> a Bloody Perſecutor, <hi>Si nobis non parcis, tibi parce, ſi non tibi, Carthagini,</hi> if thou wilt not ſpare us, yet ſpare thy ſelf, if not thy ſelf, yet ſpare thy City <hi>Carthage.</hi> But it ſutes beſt with our Text to look a little, into that which befell the <hi>Jews</hi> after their Crucifixion of our Lord, they had many <hi>Prodigies,</hi> which did foreſhew their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and the deſolations did anſwer their Prodigies. A <hi>Star</hi> is ſeen over the City like a <hi>Flaming Sword, Armies of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> ſeen in the Air, a <hi>Cow</hi> at the <hi>Altar</hi> Calves a <hi>Lamb,</hi> the <hi>Brazen gates</hi> of the Temple notwithſtanding their Locks and and Bolts, flew open in the night, <hi>Voices</hi> heard from Heaven <hi>(migremus hinc)</hi> let us go hence, one <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſon of <hi>Ananias,</hi> went about four years, crying, <hi>Woe, Woe, Woe, to Jeruſalem.</hi> Now the Vengeance was every way correſpondent to the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of it, <hi>one million of Jews</hi> ſlain by Sword, Famine, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, near <hi>one hundred thouſand</hi> made Captives and Slaves, the tender Mothers and delicate Women, Eat their own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of a Span long; the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſaith, that there was one Woman, that in the bitterneſs of her diſtreſs, ſlew and boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Son, and preſently Eat a part of him, we may ſuppoſe the Head, or an Arm, or a Leg, and then laid up the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93566:7"/> not long after, ſome of the ſeditious Bloody Villains of the City came to her, threatning her with preſent Death, unleſs ſhe would bring forth what Proviſion ſhe had, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately brought forth that part of her Child which remained, at the ſad ſight whereof, even thoſe mercileſs wretches were ſmitten with ſudden horror and amazement, inſomuch, that the Mother ſpake to them, ſaying, What! will you be more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate than a Mother? Will not you Eat where I have Eaten? But of this we need ſay no more, becauſe the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is in many of your Hands: Only obſerve that in the Prophet <hi>Amos, ch.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, for three Tranſgreſſions of Tyrus, and for four I will not turn away the Puniſhment thereof, becauſe they delivered up the whole Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to Edom, and remembred not the Brotherly Covenant,</hi> v. 10. <hi>but I will ſend a Fire on the Walls of Tyrus, which ſhall devour the Pallaces thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we may obſerve, that though the Lord be Gracious, and Mercifull, and Long-ſuffering, bearing with <hi>Three ſins,</hi> many ſins; yet when it comes to the <hi>Fourth ſin,</hi> which is <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> he will not pardon. <hi>Damaſcus fourth ſin</hi> was <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> v. 3. ſo <hi>Gaza,</hi> v. 6. ſo <hi>Edom,</hi> v. 11. ſo <hi>Ammon,</hi> v. 13. ſo <hi>Tyrus,</hi> v. 9, 10. which delivered up the whole Captivity to <hi>Edom,</hi> there had once been a Brotherly Covenant, between <hi>Solomon</hi> King of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Hiram</hi> King of <hi>Tirus,</hi> but that it ſeems was forgotten, and the <hi>Tyrians</hi> became Treacherous and Cruel, for which the Lord did wonderfully chaſtiſe them by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who after a <hi>fourteen years</hi> Siege, made <hi>Tyrus</hi> Deſolate. <hi>Tyrus</hi> was a famous City, built upon a Rock in an Iſland in the midſt of the Sea, <hi>her Merchants were Princes,</hi> her Houſes were Pallaces but no ſtrength of any Place or People, by Nature or Art, or both, can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure againſt thoſe ſharp Arrows which God hath ordained for thoſe that inhumanely Perſecute their Brethren.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thoſe that have <hi>Bowels of compaſſion, ſhould mourn upon the proſpect they have of the miſeries</hi> which <hi>will follow</hi> a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Lord <hi>wept</hi> and lamented over <hi>Jeruſalem; O</hi> Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, <hi>that Killeſt the Prophets, and Stoneſt them that are</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93566:7"/> 
               <hi>ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy Children toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther even as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not; behold your Houſe is left to you deſolate,</hi> Mat. 23. 37, 38. Luk. 19. 41. It eminently appears, that our Lords Love was great to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in that after he aroſe from the Dead, when he charged the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to Preach Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins to all Nations, he gave them particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Direction <hi>to begin at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 47. that that very place, that had drawn upon it ſelf the guilt of his precious Blood, might have the firſt offer of Salvation by its Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tells us, that his <hi>Bowels ſhould ſound like a Harp for Moab, and his inward part for Kirhareſh, chap.</hi> 16. 11. this <hi>Kirhareſh</hi> was <hi>Heliopolis</hi> the City of the Sun, where the <hi>Sun</hi> was the Idol of Worſhip, but <hi>Moab</hi> is not blamed barely for her Superſtition and Idolatry, there is <hi>Perſecution</hi> laid to her charge, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Moab</hi> reproached the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, in their Captive ſtate as <hi>Outcaſts,</hi> and would give them no Protection, quite forgetting that the Jews were a-kin to <hi>Moab;</hi> thence the Prophet foreſeeing that the Golden Vial of Wrath, would be poured forth upon <hi>Moab,</hi> within three or four years, <hi>v.</hi> 14. crys out, that <hi>his Bowels ſhould ſound like a Harp for Moab,</hi> (i. e.) their Miſeries would be ſuch as ſhould touch the Bowels of all that ever heard of it.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1. Exam. <hi>The Church of England</hi> profeſſes, at this day, before God, Angels and Men, to bewail her Sins, to take ſhame, and turn to the Lord our God, that he may have mercy upon us, and Heal our Land Now if we muſt <hi>Mourn</hi> for <hi>Englands</hi> Sins, 'tis fit that we ſhould <hi>know</hi> them; ſometimes the Sin of a Nation is ſo Open, notorious, and viſible that it may be found <hi>without ſecret ſearch,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 34. but it is not always thus, for we read there was once, <hi>[Herem] Anathema,</hi> an <hi>Accurſed Thing</hi> hidden <hi>inter Supellectilia, among the Stuff,</hi> Joſhua 7. 11. <hi>Joſhua</hi> that famous Servant of the Lord, was owned by miracles, and crowned with Succeſs and Victory, till he came before the <hi>City of Ai,</hi> where <hi>Iſrael</hi> fled before their Enemies; whereupon the Hearts of all the people melted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93566:8"/> as <hi>Water</hi> ver. 5. and <hi>Joſhua</hi> rent his cloaths, and fell to the earth upon his face, before <hi>the Ark of the Lord</hi> until the Even-Tide, he, and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and put duſt upon their heads, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid, <hi>Alas, O Lord God, wherefore haſt thou at all brought this people over Iordan, to deliver us into the hands of the Amorites to deſtroy us? Would to God we had been content and dwelt on the other ſide Iordan. O Lord what ſhall I ſay, when Iſrael turneth their backs before their enemies?</hi> ver. 7, 8. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Iſrael hath ſinned, and they have alſo tranſgreſſed my Covenant, which I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, for they have even taken of the Accurſed thing, and have alſo ſtolen, and diſſembled; alſo they have put it even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their own Stuff,</hi> ver. 10, 11. It cannot be thought but that the <hi>Tribes of Iſrael</hi> were ſtained with thoſe Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, which commonly accompany ſo great an Hoſt, ſuch as <hi>Lying, Swearing, Intemperance, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> and the like, and yet the wrath of the Lord kindled among them at this time, <hi>for a hidden wickedneſs,</hi> which few or none took notice of, <hi>the Accurſed Thing,</hi> which provoked the anger of the Lord, was <hi>hidden among the Stuff.</hi> The Sins of <hi>England</hi> are many and great at this day, the Lord be merciful unto us; and to our whole Land. <hi>Pride, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Whoredom, Swearing</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> of every kind, reign every where, <hi>Conformiſt and Nonconformiſt</hi> have great reaſon to lye in the Duſt together, becauſe of theſe Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; But, beſides all theſe Sins, 'tis poſſible, there may be ſome <hi>Achan,</hi> ſome <hi>Accurſed thing</hi> amongſt <hi>us,</hi> which hath not been taken notice of; <hi>The children are come to the Birth, and there is no ſtrength to bring forth;</hi> more mens hands are upon their Loins, than upon their <hi>Swords:</hi> we are filled with the Alarms of War, and no one knows <hi>how long:</hi> Let none take that ill, which is done in Integrity, I muſt ſearch among the <hi>Stuff</hi> for the <hi>Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing,</hi> which is a work ſo hazardous, and unaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that I could not ſubdue my ſelf to the undertaking, but by the ſence of my duty to God, and my Country.</p>
            <p>The Stuff, which I ſuſpect, and muſt ſearch into, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Affairs,</hi> and I will ſee by the help
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93566:8"/> of God, whether <hi>the Accurſed thing,</hi> be not hid under the <hi>covering of Decency and Order, Penal Laws, Laws for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, Subſcriptions, Declarations, Liturgies, Articles, Laws for Ceremonies, and Forms of Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis as clear as the Sun, that for near <hi>thirty years</hi> now laſt paſt, <hi>ſixteen hundred</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, if not more, have ſuffered very hard things upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by reaſon of great Fines, long Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, ſome of thoſe who were wont to break the Spiritual Bread, have died for want of their natural Bread, both the Shepherds and the Flocks have been ſtarv'd in their ſeveral kinds. Many Thouſands of the Families of the Proteſtant Diſſenters have been ſorely diſtreſſed by Penal Laws upon the account of Religion. And if the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of our Brethren were written at large, as the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Saints at other times have been. Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> his book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> would be but an <hi>Enchiridion</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of it.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay that the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> have been buffeted for their faults, in all this time, and that the <hi>Church of England</hi> is Innocent; that it was her duty, and became her Wiſdom, though it was not ſo agreeable to the ſweetneſs of her nature, and meekneſs of her diſpoſition, yet it became her Wiſdom, as the chaſt and tender ſpouſe of Chriſt to lay aſide the <hi>Scepter</hi> and the <hi>Dove,</hi> and to take into her hand the <hi>bloody Club of Cain</hi> to Martyr the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> into conformity: To this I reply, Let's have a fair hearing before we be Judged. The Oppreſſion and Perſecution of the truth is a great Sin, where e're 'tis found. The Church in her Prayers for this day ſeems not to make any confeſſion for this Sin, ſhe thinks her hands are clean, <hi>ſhe eats and wipes her mouth, and ſays ſhe has done no wickedneſs,</hi> Prov. 30. 20. and yet 'tis a <hi>Biſhop</hi> that ſays, though it was ſaid indeed before he was <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in <hi>his preface to the Relation of the death of the primitive Perſecutors,</hi> that they <hi>who let themſelves looſe, to all the Rages of a mad Proſecution of ſome poor undiſcreet and deluded People, ought ſeriouſly to profeſs their Repentance</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93566:9"/> 
               <hi>of this fury, in Inſtances, that may be as viſible and edifying as their rage hath been publick and Deſtructive,</hi> And now we proceed to <hi>Examine,</hi> whether ſome drops of <hi>Abels</hi> blood may not be found in the <hi>skirts of England,</hi> and ſearch into the <hi>Stuff,</hi> that we may know whether there be any <hi>Accurſed thing hid in it;</hi> That we may accordingly govern our ſelves in theſe days of Faſting and Lamentation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt thing</hi> we ſhall conſider, that was impoſed upon the Nonconformiſts is, <hi>the ſubſcription in the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> with the <hi>Oath in the Oxford Act,</hi> in which are theſe words, <hi>I A. B. do declare, that it is not lawful upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>I A. B. do ſwear that it is not lawful,—</hi>We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed thus to declare and ſwear; and here obſerve theſe <hi>three things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> a man may believe a Propoſition to be true, though it be diſputable, which yet he would not be willing to ſwear that it was true; As I believe the <hi>Pope to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> yet I am not willing to ſwear that the Pope is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; I believe by <hi>Myſtical Babylon is meant Rome,</hi> I believe the Saints in Heaven know not our affairs here, yet I ſhould be unwilling to ſwear it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>Barclay Grotius</hi> and others, who have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Largely in favour of the Prerogative of Crowned Heads, do yet allow that there are ſome caſes, in which it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Subject to take Arms againſt the King, and if the King turns <hi>Tyrant,</hi> Governing not by Law, but by his own Will, he doth <hi>Excidere de jure, etſi haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>England,</hi> all the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all the Proteſtant Princes beyond the Seas in their Proceedings, againſt the late King <hi>James,</hi> have juſtified the Nonconformiſts in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing the <hi>Oxford Oath,</hi> Whoſe turn is it to take ſhame now?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second thing</hi> we muſt conſider, is that about <hi>Re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> as though Ordination by Presbyters and Paſtors of Churches, were not ſufficient,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93566:9"/> without the laying on of the Hands of thoſe we now call <hi>Biſhops, Lords Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Word of God, in the New Teſtament, makes no difference between the <hi>Biſhop and the Presbyter,</hi> or Paſtor of a Church. He that is a Paſtor of a Church of Chriſt, is a Goſpel <hi>Biſhop, Chriſts Biſhop, Act.</hi> 20. 17, 28. the ſame perſons that are called <hi>Presbyters</hi> in one place, or <hi>Elders,</hi> are in the other called <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Overſeers.</hi> So <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7. <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> was ordained by the laying on of the Hands of the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. of this Judgment were <hi>Auguſtine, Jerom, Chryſoſtome,</hi> with many others among the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. All our Learned Divines at the Reformation from Popery, held that the Ordination by the Paſtors of Churches was valid and good, the 23 <hi>Article, of miniſtring in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi> ſeems to ſpeak as much; of this Judgment are the <hi>French Churches, Belgick</hi> and <hi>Helvetick</hi> Churches, beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others. I need not name the <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi> for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath juſtified all our Nonconformity, by reſtoring the ejected Miniſters to their places, as of old.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops</hi> may glory over us, as the Kings <hi>Biſhops, Biſhops of the State,</hi> but they muſt not pretend to be ſo near in Blood to the <hi>Scripture Biſhops,</hi> of the firſt <hi>two hundred years,</hi> as the Paſtors of ſingle Congregations; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, that Ordination by the hands of the Paſtors of Churches, filled with the Holy Ghoſt, is much more eligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than by <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third point</hi> we muſt conſider, is the <hi>Declaration</hi> in the Act of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which is this; <hi>I A. B. do here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent, to all and every thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and preſcribed in and by the Book, Intituled the Book of Common Prayer.</hi> Here we refuſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>matter of Aſſent.</hi> Many things might be named, but one ſhall ſuffice; we can't <hi>Aſſent</hi> to that paſſage in the <hi>Creed,</hi> commonly called <hi>Athanaſius Creed,</hi> where 'tis ſaid, that every one that doth not <hi>keep that Faith whole, ſhall without doubt periſh Everlaſtingly.</hi> Now one Article of that <hi>Creed</hi> is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93566:10"/> about <hi>the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Father and the Son,</hi> which the <hi>Greek Churches</hi> did not Believe nor receive; If I believe it was an Error in the <hi>Greek Churches,</hi> and that they ſee not clearly into that Myſtery, yet I muſt be very bold, if I leap into the Throne of Judgment, and pronounce them Loſt and Damned. The Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Father and the Son, is a moſt profound Myſtery, and very much obſcured, by bringing in <hi>that</hi> word <hi>Proceſſion;</hi> Which the Scripture on that occaſion never uſes. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> indeed ſolemnly <hi>Anathematizes</hi> the <hi>Greeks in Bulla Coenae</hi> every <hi>Maundy Thurſday,</hi> as ſo many Schiſmaticks and Apoſtates: 'Tis a conſiderable point of Popery, to curſe and deſtroy all that ſeem to differ from us in Opinion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the <hi>matter of conſent,</hi> we cannot conſent to every thing contained, and preſcribed in and by the Book, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the <hi>Book of Common Prayer.</hi> I intend not to ſpeak of the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the <hi>Surplice,</hi> becauſe all know they came <hi>from Rome,</hi> and when <hi>Rome</hi> falls they will fall too. Neither ſhall I look into the <hi>Prayers of the Church,</hi> though that is no very commendable paſſage, wherewith ſhe is ſo oft upbraided, in praying that the Late King <hi>James,</hi> a profeſt Papiſt, might <hi>perſevere in the Faith;</hi> but, that which I ſhall account for, is our Refuſal to Read the impoſed Form of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> a point a little more difficult, but not leſs material than that of <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> and here pray judge between <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and the <hi>Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>Firſt, During the <hi>Apoſtles time,</hi> and <hi>two or three hundred years</hi> after, there was no <hi>Liturgy</hi> uſed nor impoſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they direct for the drawing up of any, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing it by Penal Laws; it hath been abundantly cleared by thoſe that have laboured in this controverſy, that the <hi>Paſtors of Churches</hi> in the primitive Times, did not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Read Prayers, de Scripto recitare:</hi> They did Read <hi>Pſalms, Chapters;</hi> but they did not Read Prayers, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 5. The Prayer of the Church for <hi>Peter</hi>'s Inlargement was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Inſtant, Fervent, <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> but not by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93566:10"/> any preſcribed Form, as is agreed upon by all ſides; ſome have been ſo curious as to obſerve, that in the Primitive Times, the Saints uſually prayed with their <hi>Eyes fixed on the Mercy-ſeat,</hi> or cloſed, which utterly diſables Perſons for Reading Prayers.</p>
            <p>2. The Paſtors of Churches in the Primitive Times, were under the <hi>teaching of the Anointing,</hi> and had the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Gift of Prayer. The <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Apol.</hi> 2. is vindicated beyond all exceptions, by which it's moſt manifeſt, that they prayed not then in their Aſſemblies, by Book or Form, but from the Gift and Ability they had. So likewiſe that of <hi>Tertullian</hi> Apol. 1. <hi>Sine monitore, quia de pectore oramus,</hi> ſhews clearly, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Primitive way of Prayer was not by preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Liturgies, but that it was the <hi>Heatheniſh way</hi> of Prayer: The <hi>Chriſtians prayed by Heart, the Heathens prayed by Book:</hi> The Heatheniſh <hi>Greeks, Perſians, Romans,</hi> had their <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> Prieſts, and Sacred Perſons, who were wont to ſay Prayers <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>out of a Book.</hi> This is a matter well known, from the Authority of <hi>Apuleius, Pauſanias, Livy, Cicero, Lactantius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. When the Chriſtians were ſo numerous at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> that it was thought convenient to Diſpoſe of them in ſeveral Churches, that zealous Emperour <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> writes to <hi>Euſebius, Biſhop of Caeſarea,</hi> for <hi>fifty Bibles,</hi> for the uſe of the Churches, but there is no mention of any one <hi>Common-Prayer-Book. Euſeb. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 34, 36.</p>
            <p>4. When Forms of Prayer began to be uſed, every Church made uſe of what Forms they pleaſed; ſo <hi>Socrates Scholaſt. lib.</hi> 5. And it appears by the <hi>Epistles</hi> of Pope <hi>Pius the Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Gregory the Thirteenth,</hi> prefixt to the <hi>Brevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Romanum,</hi> that the ſeveral Churches of the <hi>Roman Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> had their ſeveral Liturgies, until that branch of the Churches Liberty was taken away by the <hi>Council of Trent.</hi> Here in <hi>England,</hi> before the Reformation, we had ſeveral Modes of <hi>Common-Prayer-Books,</hi> ſome after the uſe of <hi>Sarum,</hi> others after the uſe of <hi>York, Lincoln,</hi> which afterward were reduced to one for publick uſe, and impoſed by <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93566:11"/>
            <p> 5. 'Twas the Ignorance, Carnality, the Sloth and Lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Clergy, together with their Pride, which firſt brought in, and impoſed Service-Books upon the Churches; as for thoſe Liturgies, which bear the Great names of St. <hi>James, Peter, Mark, Clemens, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Chryſostom—</hi>they are known Forgeries. When the Church began to be an <hi>Harlot;</hi> when <hi>Biſhops</hi> were not <hi>Silver Trumpets,</hi> but <hi>Tinkling Cymbals, Clouds without Water, Bells without Clappers,</hi> and <hi>Breaſts without Milk;</hi> when the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in Councils, as of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> profeſt they did <hi>Literas ignorare,</hi> and could not <hi>write</hi> their <hi>own Names</hi> to confirm their Canons, then came in our Liturgies.</p>
            <p>6. 'Tis no part of our buſineſs to enquire whether in ſome caſes it may not be lawful to uſe a Set Form of Prayer; but I would ſatisfie you in this, that our way of Worſhip, without the Reſtraint of Set Forms, is moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the way of Worſhip, uſed by the Holy Apoſtles, and by the Primitive times, for many hundreds of years paſt before Set Forms were uſed, and many hundreds more before they were impoſed. Now I muſt deſire you to obſerve this one thing, that there is great difference between <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing a Set Form, and Impoſing it,</hi> which I ſhall clear to you thus. We find <hi>Levit.</hi> 5. 7. that there was proviſion made for ſuch as were <hi>Poor</hi> in their Eſtates, that if they were <hi>not able</hi> to bring for a <hi>Treſpaſs-Offering,</hi> or Sin-Offering, a <hi>Lamb, or Kid of the Goats,</hi> he might bring <hi>Two Turtle-Doves,</hi> or <hi>Two young Pigeons,</hi> which the Lord would <hi>accept of;</hi> but if a Rich man, that had Flocks and Herds, had brought <hi>Two young Pigeons,</hi> the Lord would have abhorred it, and much more, if all the Rich men in <hi>Iſrael</hi> had agreed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, from a principle of Covetouſneſs, in making a Law, that it ſhould be <hi>penal</hi> for any man, be he Rich or Poor, to bring any thing for a <hi>Sin-Offering,</hi> beſides <hi>Two young Pigeons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many perſons in the Churches may be poor in Parts, and in Gifts, and may need the help of a <hi>Set Form of Prayer,</hi> but to <hi>Impoſe</hi> by Law a Set Form upon all, be their ability for Prayer never ſo great, is to bind us up to the offering of <hi>Doves and Pigeons,</hi> when we are able to bring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93566:11"/> before the Lord, <hi>Lambs, Kids and Bullocks;</hi> this were a Law to be diſliked: Or thus, whereas the condition of ſome that are Lame and Impotent, requires the <hi>help of Crutches to go to Market,</hi> and they are to be pitied under their Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet if a Law were made, that every man that comes to <hi>Market without Crutches,</hi> ſhould <hi>loſe one of his Ears,</hi> you would all cry out, that it was an unequal and unrighteous Law: Some may need and uſe Set Forms, but to Impoſe them upon all under ſevere and terrible Penalties, is that which hath no warrant from Scripture, nor the firſt and beſt Ages of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Fourth Point</hi> we are to look into, is, that <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> required by the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which concerns the <hi>Covenant;</hi> it runs thus, <hi>I do declare, that I do hold there Lies no obligation upon me, or any other perſon, from the Oath commonly called the Solemn League or Covenant, to endeavour any Change or Alteration of the Government, either in Church or State, and that the ſame in it ſelf was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Oath, and Impoſed on the Subjects of the Realm, againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</hi> We have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to Renounce this Covenant; now conſider what we ſay for our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are many uſeful Preachers, and Men of good Learning, that never read a Law-book in their Lives; they know nothing of <hi>Magna Charta, Bracton, Littleton, Cook, Common Law, Statute Law—</hi>Is it reaſonable then to require them to Declare the <hi>Covenant</hi> is contrary to <hi>known Laws</hi> and Liberties, which they are utterly unacquainted with?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though I am one of thoſe that never took the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, yet when I conſider, That the <hi>King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, have taken it, 'tis a very ſtrange thing, if it ſhould bind none of them, <hi>not one of them:</hi> A man had need ſpend ſome years in <hi>Caſuistical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> and read all the Books which are Extant <hi>De Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Juramenti,</hi> before he abſolve two or three Kingdoms, and declare underſtandingly that no one man is bound by that Oath, which almoſt every man took.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the Covenant all perſons were bound in their places
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93566:12"/> to endeavour a <hi>Reformation</hi> of the Church, according to <hi>the Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>the Examples of the Beſt Reformed Churches;</hi> is this an unlawful Oath? if a man ſhould ſwear, that in his Place and Calling he would endeavour with all his might to caſt <hi>every Idol out of the World,</hi> we ſee our <hi>King, the Lords and Commons of</hi> Scotland, have caſt off <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Presbytery:</hi> But I will ſpeak no more to this Subject. By what you have heard, you may judge whether we have been <hi>ſtraining at Gnats,</hi> or other men have <hi>ſwallowed Camels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth Point,</hi> and the <hi>Laſt</hi> we ſhall take notice of, is that paſſage in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> concerning the <hi>Commination, or Denouncing of Gods Anger and Judgments againſt ſinners,</hi> which begins thus, <hi>Curſed is the man, that maketh any Carved or Graven Image to worſhip it; Curſed is he, that curſeth his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother: Curſed is he, that removeth his Neighbours Land-mark; And all the People are to ſay, Amen.</hi> In the <hi>Preface</hi> to this <hi>Commination</hi> we have words to this purpoſe, That until <hi>the Godly Diſcipline of the Primitive Church may be reſtored again, which is much to be wiſhed, it is thought good, inſtead thereof, to Read the general ſentences of Gods curſing againſt impenitent ſinners, and that the People ſhould anſwer to every ſentence, Amen.</hi> Upon this occaſion I have theſe things to preſent to your meditation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That thoſe Excellent Perſons our Reformers, and Compilers of this Book of Common-Prayer, had no full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in what was then done; They ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, they came ſhort of the <hi>Godly Diſcipline of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times,</hi> and that the Reformation ſhould have been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on higher, if the Times would have given leave, and yet they had then their Government by <hi>Biſhops, Arch-biſhops, Chancellors, Registers, Arch-deacons, Surrogates and Proctors,</hi> as we have at this day. But as <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the Licenſe of Divorces, becauſe of the <hi>Jews hardneſs of heart, but from the beginning it was not ſo;</hi> in like manner our Reformers direct to this way of <hi>Commination and Curſing,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Antient Diſcipline,</hi> allowing <hi>that from the beginning it was not ſo, Matth.</hi> 19. 8.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93566:12"/>
            <p> Secondly, 'Tis more than a hundred years ſince theſe Good men firſt recorded their hearty deſires and <hi>wiſhes,</hi> for a higher, and more compleat Reformation, in theſe words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſtored again, which is much to be wiſhed;</hi> and it is enough that the Church carries her <hi>Good Wiſhes</hi> with her through all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. The <hi>Biſhop of Sarum</hi> in his excellent Sermon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. 15. before the Houſe of Commons, calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to <hi>carry the Reformation higher,</hi> as they deſire to ſee the Church and State to proſper. <hi>You can concur in giving the laſt finiſhings to our Reformation, many of the old Corruptions do yet remain among us in practice, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Eccleſiaſtical Authority is liable to great Objections. I will not run out into farther particulars, for it will be eaſie to find them, and if you once ſet about it, you will ſoon ſee what work there is before you.</hi> Now if after all, there be nothing done for the <hi>Lord</hi> and his Houſe, then will theſe <hi>wiſhes</hi> of our Reformers ſtand as a Teſtimony againſt our <hi>Prelates</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Many of the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Holy Men</hi> of old, fell into great Trouble by ſtanding up in their places for a Reformation. <hi>Idolatrous Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel</hi> made <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> weary of his Life. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet was (as <hi>Dorotheus</hi> ſaith) <hi>ſawn aſunder</hi> for oppoſing the Corruptions of his time: The <hi>Holy Apoſtles</hi> were charged by the <hi>Jews,</hi> though moſt falſly, that <hi>they turned the World upſide down,</hi> Acts 17. 6. and accordingly they ſought their Deſtruction. Our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came in the <hi>time for Reformation,</hi> Heb. 9. 10. and purſued it ſo cloſely, that the rage of the <hi>Jews, the Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees</hi> was kindled againſt him, and nothing but his Blood ſhed by falſe Accuſation upon the Croſs could quench it: We may compare <hi>John</hi> 2. 15. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 12. where we find him cleanſing the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>And he made a Scourge of ſmall Cords, he drove them all out of the Temple, and the Sheep, and the Oxen, and pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the Changers Money, and overthrew the Tables—</hi>In
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93566:13"/> this <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſeems to have been his <hi>Type, ch.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>and it grieved me ſore, therefore I caſt forth all the Houſhold-ſtuff of Tobiah out of the Chambers of the Houſe of the Lord;</hi> 'tis a dangerous, yet a needful work to Cleanſe and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: Our Lord Chriſt owned it, and upon that which our Lord Chriſt did of this kind, we may make theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That with this <hi>Reforming work,</hi> our Lord began, and ended his Miniſtry, not once but twice, did he caſt <hi>the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple,</hi> Diſeaſes are apt to return upon the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſcourged them out as ſo many <hi>Beaſts,</hi> to ſhew that he was a <hi>Lion</hi> as well as a <hi>Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That in that neceſſary work he had no regard to his own ſafety, the zeal of the Lords Houſe eat it up.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Men will never part with their gainful corruptions, till conſtrained by the rod.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Lord makes a ſcourge for thoſe that were wont to make a <hi>ſcourge</hi> for others, that diſliked their Corruptions in worſhip, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 17.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Thoſe are vile and baſe, and as ſo many <hi>Beaſts</hi> in our Lords account, that are enemies to Reformation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That which the Nonconformiſts</hi> of theſe Three Kingdoms, have Written for, Preached for, and Suffered for, is, that the <hi>Godly Worſhip, and Godly Diſcipline of the Primitive Church may bereſtored, which is much to be wiſhed,</hi> So it was ſaid by our Fathers, ſo it is now ſaid by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and ſo we alſo ſay at this day; It was no crime heretofore, nay 'tis no crime now, when the Church-men ſay we need a farther Reformation, and it can be no crime in us neither; why then ſhould we be afraid? That
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93566:13"/> expreſſion about the <hi>Godly Diſcipline</hi> ſtands in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as well for the <hi>Juſtification of the Nonconformiſts as for a Teſtimony againſt the Prelates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, It was the Glory of <hi>Moſes that he was faithful in the houſe of God</hi> Heb. 3. 5. He did all things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to the pattern in the Mount,</hi> it was alſo the Glory of <hi>King Solomon,</hi> that in building of the Temple, and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things about the <hi>Porch, Courts, Chambers, the Altars, Lavers, Tables and golden Candleſticks,</hi> he kept preciſely to divine direction, as in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. 11-19. <hi>The Lord made me underſtand in writing by his hand upon me. Even all the works of this pattern;</hi> now if this were the Glory of theſe great men to keep to the Rule, it can never be our ſhame to walk in their ſteps, and follow their example, preſſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to have all things in Gods Houſe according to <hi>the Pattern in the Mount:</hi> Having this occaſion to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the Magnificent Temple, which he built, 'tis our preſent concernment to ſtand ſtill a little and make ſome ſhort reflectiosn upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay, the firſt fixt place for ſolemn worſhip that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God appointed was <hi>Solomons Temple;</hi> The <hi>Tabernacle of Moſes</hi> was indeed the Place for Divine Service, to which the Tribes were to reſort: But then the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> was a <hi>walking Temple,</hi> ſometimes at <hi>Shilo,</hi> ſometimes elſe where; For the ſpace of about 500 <hi>years</hi> from <hi>Moſes to Solomon,</hi> there was no <hi>fixt Place</hi> for worſhip, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Temple</hi> was.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the only fixt place for ſolemn worſhip by the immediate deſignation and appointment of God, was the <hi>Temple at Jeruſalem;</hi> to the beſt of my knowledge there was never any before, or ſince, <hi>John</hi> 4. 21. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto her, Woman, believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet in Jeruſalem worſhip the Father; God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit, and in truth,</hi> ver. 24.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93566:14"/> 3. Though there had been many <hi>Temples</hi> in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> uſed by the Natives in Honour of their falſe Gods; yet the Lord would make uſe of none of them, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects they ſhould be all demoliſhed and a new one built, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Ye ſhall utterly deſtroy all the places, wherein the Nations which ye ſhall poſſeſs, ſerved their Gods, upon the Mountains, and upon the Hills, and under every green Tree; The Land of Canaan</hi> was a place of learning before <hi>Iſrael</hi> came into it, and of <hi>Religion</hi> too; but it was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with ſuperſtition and Idolatry, in <hi>Joſh.</hi> 15. 15, 42. We read of <hi>Kirjath Sepher, Kirjath Sanna Cities of Books, of learning</hi> or <hi>the Law</hi> called <hi>Deber,</hi> as the <hi>Oracle</hi> for <hi>Wiſdom, Eloquence, and Acuteneſs;</hi> theſe <hi>Temples</hi> were Rich and pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous, ſo far as we can gueſs by the remains we have of the Hiſtory of thoſe Times; yet the Lord in his Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie would have none of them ſpared, for Synagogues or Houſes of Prayer, becauſe they had been ſet apart for Idolatrous purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let's obſerve, the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of the Place, which the Wiſdom of God ſingles forth out of all the world, where his <hi>Holy Temple</hi> ſhould be built, 'twas <hi>Ornans Threſhing floor,</hi> 2 Chron. 3. 1. with the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 18. <hi>Then</hi> Solomon <hi>began to build the Houſe of the Lord at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>in mount</hi> Moriah, <hi>where the Lord appeared unto</hi> David <hi>his Father in the Place that</hi> David <hi>had prepared in the Threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floor of</hi> Ornan <hi>the Jebuſite.</hi> There were many places at that time, where the Holy People were wont to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as <hi>Gilgal, Shilo, illa omnia poſt-ponit,</hi> but the Lord ſlights all theſe, and chooſes the <hi>Threſhing floor</hi> of <hi>Ornan the Jebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,</hi> it's likely that this <hi>Ornan</hi> was of Princely deſcent as he had a Princely mind, which could readily part with any worldly Intereſt for Gods Service and Honour; his mind was as great as his Birth, and his devotion equal to both, there might be ſome myſtery in this choice, which the Lord made of the <hi>Threſhing Floor</hi> of <hi>Ornan,</hi> to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93566:14"/> 1. That Temple-Work is hard work, 'tis <hi>Threſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That Temple-Work is to ſeparate between the <hi>Chaff and the Wheat,</hi> the precious and the vile.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the ſeparation will not be perfect, till the end of all things, <hi>mali in area nobiſcum eſſe poſſunt, in horreo non poſſunt.</hi> The wicked may mingle with us in the <hi>Floor,</hi> they ſhall not in the <hi>Garner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let's conſider what the <hi>Heathen</hi> would ſay of this <hi>Temple at Jeruſalem,</hi> which was the moſt magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent and ſtately ſtructure in the World, excelling in glory: no doubt but they would load it with Reproaches, and ſay, This Temple upon which <hi>King Solomon</hi> ſpent a <hi>hundred thouſand Talents of Gold, and a thouſand thouſand Talents of Silver,</hi> is after all but <hi>Ornan's Threſhing-floor;</hi> 'tis but a <hi>Barn;</hi> our Temples are <hi>Holy Places,</hi> and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before that at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Now I have great aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that <hi>King Solomon</hi> with all his wiſdom was able to vindicate the <hi>Houſe of God</hi> which he had built, and upon a fair hearing, to confound all thoſe that diſgraced it, <hi>King Solomon</hi> could tell thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> that all their Temples were ſtained with Superſtition and Idolatry, which <hi>Ornan's Threſhing-floor</hi> never was: All their <hi>Temples</hi> were places of <hi>Spiritual Whoredoms,</hi> they were Erected by <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and Conſecrated for <hi>Idolatrous uſes,</hi> and that his <hi>Temple at Jeruſalem</hi> did as much excel all the Temples of the Heathen, as <hi>a pure ſpotleſs Virgin doth an old wrinkled Harlot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall now quit this Uſe of Examination, and ſearch no further into <hi>the ſtuff.</hi> The Proteſtant Diſſenters dare not flatter the Prerogatives of Princes, to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; they dare not <hi>Aſſent and Conſent</hi> ſolemnly to that which they inwardly diſlike; they dare not depart from that <hi>Ordination,</hi> which is according to the Scriptures,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93566:15"/> and the practice of the pureſt Churches; they dare not offer to the Lord <hi>that which coſts them nothing,</hi> nor ſubmit to thoſe Forms of Prayer, which <hi>quench the Spirit of Prayer;</hi> they dare not <hi>renounce Covenants, as contrary to the known Laws,</hi> when the Laws to them are <hi>utterly unknown;</hi> they dare not but appear humbly in their places for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of the <hi>Godly Diſcipline of the Primitive Church,</hi> ſince all allow 'tis to be <hi>wiſhed for;</hi> they dare not but with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> keep to the <hi>pattern in the Mount,</hi> notwithſtanding the Inventions and Commandments of Men; and if in all theſe things the Nonconformiſts are in the <hi>right,</hi> and have in their <hi>Sackcloth</hi> witneſſed to the Truth, then ought the <hi>Church of England to hang down her head, ſmite upon her breaſt, and walk ſoftly,</hi> becauſe ſhe hath been <hi>cruel like the Oſtrich in the Wilderneſs, the Tongue of the ſucking Child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth, for thirſt, the young Children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them; they that did feed delicately, are deſolate in the ſtreets; they that were brought up in Scarlet, embrace Dunghills,</hi> Lam. 4. 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>We come now to the <hi>Second Uſe,</hi> which is for <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,</hi> and here let me beg and beſeech you to lay aſide all conſideration of our own and our Brethrens Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and, <hi>as the Elect of God, put on bowels of compaſſion, Col.</hi> 3. 12. It will be ſome evidence to us, that we are the <hi>elect of God,</hi> if we can put on <hi>bowels of Mercy,</hi> if we can ſay in ſincerity, as I hope we ſhall, O that <hi>our head, were Waters and our eyes fountains of tears that we might make our Meeting Place a Bochim,</hi> Judg. 2. 5. A place of bitter mourning, <hi>like the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Megiddo,</hi> Zech. 12. 11. Becauſe of all the Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and Abominations of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> the cry of our Sins is gone up to Heaven againſt us, O let us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by the cry of our Prayers and Tears, to ſilence the cry of our Sins, <hi>O Lord God, put bowels of mercy into every one of us;</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew language</hi> one word, <hi>(Rahem)</hi> ſignifies both Bowels and Mercy, and by a <hi>Metatheſis</hi> of the <hi>Radical Letters,</hi> is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93566:15"/> made <hi>(herein)</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Anathema,</hi> to ſhew, that if we are without <hi>bowels of Mercy</hi> in this day of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Diſtreſs, we are under the <hi>Curſe,</hi> and none of the Elect of God. It is a <hi>Cain's mark</hi> upon <hi>Judas,</hi> he loſt his <hi>bowels, Acts</hi> 1. 18. and upon King <hi>Jehoram</hi> too, that he was <hi>diſeaſed in his bowels,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 15. O! let us mingle our <hi>hearts</hi> and our <hi>prayers,</hi> no leſs than our Faith, with the holy Word of God as we go along, and cry aloud, that the <hi>God of all Grace,</hi> and Father of Mercies, would pleaſe to heal the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> which is in our <hi>bowels,</hi> and in the bowels of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> There is ſomething peculiar in the Judgments, which have been armed againſt <hi>us</hi> of this Generation, here in <hi>England.</hi> There was in our <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>London</hi> ſuch a <hi>conſuming Peſtilence,</hi> as our Fathers never ſaw, there they died by thouſands, where now they walk by thouſands; there was ſuch a <hi>devouring Fire</hi> as our Fathers never ſaw, a <hi>Fire,</hi> which had not learnt to diſtinguiſh between ſacred and prophane, between the Bible and the Comedy, between places of common Exchange, and more Divine Commerce; And <hi>for all this his Anger is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill, Iſa.</hi> 5. 25. Our condition at this day is ſomewhat prodigious, we are, and have been, for almoſt two years under the Influence of <hi>two Suns,</hi> Alas for the Miſeries and Deſolations of <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is the ſound of the Trumpet, the Alarms of War, there is the devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sword, there are Garments rouled in Blood; <hi>Alas</hi> for diſconſolate and deſolate <hi>Ireland;</hi> her Towns are Burnt, her Houſes are Spoiled, her Virgins Raviſhed, all places filled with Confuſion and Slaughter. <hi>Ireland</hi> is now an <hi>Aceldema, a Field of Blood.</hi> But Glory, Glory to him, that ſits on the Throne, and to the Lamb, for ever and ever, the <hi>Virgin Daughter</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> begins to awake, and ariſe out of the Duſt, to ſit and ſing as in the days of her Youth, as in the days when ſhe came <hi>up out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Now is fulfilled that which was ſpoken by</hi> Iſaias <hi>the Prophet, ſaying, The Land of</hi> Zebulun, <hi>and the Land of</hi> Nephthalim, <hi>by the way of the Sea, beyond</hi> Jordan, Galilee <hi>of the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>the people which ſate in</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93566:16"/> 
               <hi>darkneſs ſaw great light, and to them which ſate in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Shadow of death, light is ſprung up,</hi> Mat. 4. 14, 15, 16. This is no new thing in the courſe of Divine Providence, that thoſe who were firſt in Trouble ſhould be Relieved firſt.</p>
            <p>There are two ways which I ſhall propoſe, wherein we ought to ſhew forth our <hi>Bowels of Mercy,</hi> for theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>By our perſonal Reformation;</hi> we <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> are more eſpecially obliged to caſt away every <hi>Idol of Gold and Silver to the Moles, and to the Bats,</hi> Iſa. 2. 20. 'Tis ſaid <hi>among the Heathen, the Lord hath done great things for us,</hi> and indeed the Lord hath done great things for us, <hi>whereof we are glad,</hi> Pſal. 126. 3, 4. He hath broken the Horn of the wicked, the Teeth of the ungodly; he hath looſed our Bands, taken the Burthen from our Shoulders, and ſet our Feet in a large place The Lord <hi>hath turned again our Captivity, and it is as the Streams in the South,</hi> which wonderfully revives and comforts thoſe that have born the heat of the day. We have often heard, that if there had been but four or five more holy Perſons in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Sodom</hi> had been ſpared, and not deſtroyed by <hi>Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven;</hi> Gen. 18 32. Methinks I hear <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> crying to us with a loud voice, If ye Love us, and have any Compaſſion for us, then turn unto the Lord unfeignedly, live like ſo many <hi>Nazarites,</hi> keep your Covenants, pay your Vows, and perfume your Houſes with the Morning and Evening Sacrifice of Prayer and Praiſe. Dearly beloved in our Lord Jeſus, ſhall it be <hi>written</hi> down by the <hi>Angels</hi> which attend our ſolemn Aſſemblies, that <hi>this Man and that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man were Born amongſt us this day?</hi> Amen, Amen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87. 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By <hi>Importunate</hi> and <hi>Fervent Prayer</hi> both for <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That God would <hi>Anoint the Eyes of</hi> England <hi>with Eye-ſalve,</hi> that ſhe may ſee into thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern her peace, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 18. Let's chuſe rather to fall a Sacrifice for <hi>England</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Proſperity, than <hi>ſow Pillows under her Elbows,</hi> Ezek. 13. 18. leſt ſhe ſleep the ſleep of Death,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93566:16"/> and become the ſcorn of Nations; Lord enlighten <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that ſhe may ſee her ſins, and acknowledge them. <hi>He that covereth his ſin ſhall not proſper, but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall find mercy,</hi> Prov. 28. 13. The word is <hi>(Peſha) Piaculum, his greater ſin,</hi> for we can readily enough confeſs our leſſer ſins, but 'tis our greater ſin, we are apt to cover, deny, excuſe or leſſen: 'Tis Death to reflect upon <hi>Herodias; England</hi> hath <hi>touched the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,</hi> and oppreſſed the <hi>Followers of the Lamb.</hi> She muſt not content her ſelf to bewail on theſe days of Solemn Faſting and Prayer her Debaucheries, though they are abominable, but ſhe muſt add to her <hi>Litany,</hi> which ſhe hath hitherto forgotten; <hi>From all the ſore Judgments of the Sword, Famine and Peſtilence, which are wont to follow the Oppreſſion and Perſecution of the Truth, Good Lord deliver us.</hi> Lord open the Eyes of <hi>England</hi> to look into her Laws, and ſee if there be none that are written in Blood; Lord open the Eyes of <hi>England</hi> to look into her Courts of Judicature, and ſee if Juſtice and Judgment have not been turn'd into <hi>Gall and Wormwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To look into her Armies, and ſee if there be no <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans,</hi> and <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> there.</p>
            <p>To look into her <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> and ſee whether that Pompous Worſhip be according to Goſpel Rule. To look into her Parochial Conſtitutions, and ſee whether <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Dumb Dogs</hi> are not ſet to watch over the Flocks, and whether there be any thing of the <hi>Godly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Primitive Church reſtored which was much wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for,</hi> when our Fathers firſt caſt off the Iron Yoke of Popery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> we ſhould earneſtly pray that the Lord would pleaſe by the Effuſion and Conviction of his Spirit, to work a National Repentance among us, that as we have ſeen a change in the State, we may be ſo happy as to ſee a change of Heart and Life: Wo be to us, if <hi>England</hi> be <hi>the door which turneth upon his hinges,</hi> Prov. 26. 14.</p>
            <p>Lord God, give us a National Repentance like to that of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> Jonah 3. 5, 10. <hi>So the People of Nineveh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved God, and Proclaimed a Faſt, and put on Sackcloth from</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93566:17"/> 
               <hi>the greateſt of them even to the leaſt of them; and God ſaw their works, that they turned from their evil ways, and God Repented of the evil, that he ſaid he would do unto them, and he did it not. Ninevehs</hi> Repentance was <hi>quick</hi> upon the firſt Sermon and Warning, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. at the motion of a Stranger, it was general <hi>King, Princes, Nobles</hi> High and Low, Rich and Poor, all in Sackcloth, nay the very Beaſts, the Herds, the Flocks, were mourners too, it was ſerious and unfeigned, <hi>they cryed mightily unto God,</hi> [ver. 8.] and Reformed their Lives, it was upon <hi>a Peradventure,</hi> [ver. 9.] like to that in <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Who knoweth if he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and Repent, and leave a Bleſſing behind him, even a meat Offering and a Drink Offering unto the Lord your God.</hi> Such a Repentance, as this would help us, as it did them when they were within <hi>fourty Days</hi> of Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>God forbid, that the Men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhould riſe up in Judgment againſt us of <hi>England, Matth.</hi> 12. 41.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us cry to the Lord on the behalf of the <hi>Court,</hi> that old Sins may not be found in our new Court, that the blemiſhes of <hi>King Charles the Second</hi> and <hi>King James the Second,</hi> may not be the ſtains of our <hi>King William the third</hi> and <hi>Queen Mary the ſecond.</hi> That the Scepter in the Hand of our <hi>King</hi> may be <hi>a Scepter of Rightouſneſs,</hi> that our <hi>Queen</hi> may be all <hi>Glorious within,</hi> that our Princes may be <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Princes of God,</hi> that the <hi>meat of their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> the <hi>ſitting of their Servants,</hi> the <hi>attendance of their Miniſters, their Apparel,</hi> and <hi>their Cup-bearers</hi> may for the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> become the wonder of the world and the Joy of Angels, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 10. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let's cry unto the Lord on the behalf of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Church of</hi> England, <hi>that the Godly worſhip and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Primitive Church may be reſtored,</hi> that ſhe may be cleanſed refined, and Adorned, with meekneſs, that no <hi>Italian ſcent</hi> may be diſcerned in her worſhip. That no Leprous ſpot be ſeen upon her Children, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 12. That all her Prieſts may be cloathed with Righteouſneſs, and all her Angels become <hi>Angels of Incenſe,</hi> that ſhe may at length burn all her <hi>bloody Rods,</hi> and be deeply humbled for <hi>Joſephs Bloody Coat,</hi> Gen. 37. 32. That ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93566:17"/> the Bleſſings of thoſe, that have been ready to Periſh may come upon her, and ſhe may look as though ſhe came down for Heaven, <hi>as a Bride adorned for her Husband,</hi> Rev. 21. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us cry unto the Lord on the behalf of our <hi>Cities,</hi> that there may ſuch a <hi>ſtream of Righteouſneſs</hi> rund down their ſtreets as may Carry away all <hi>falſe weights and meaſures,</hi> Amos 5. 24. That there may be as much care to Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualize Trade as to Enlarge it, that our Citizens may be wiſe <hi>Merchants</hi> ſelling all to buy <hi>the goodly Pearl,</hi> of <hi>Greateſt price,</hi> Matth. 13. 45. 46. That our Cities might by their Virtue, Juſtice and Holineſs, acquire to themſelves the new name in the Prophet, <hi>Jehovah Shammah,</hi> the Lord is there. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48. 35.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let's cry to the Lord on the behalf of the <hi>Camp,</hi> that our Officers and Soldiers may lay aſide all Weapons of unrighteouſneſs and do violence to no man; that they may not fight under the <hi>Banner</hi> of the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs</hi> nor carry the <hi>mark of the Beaſt</hi> in their <hi>Foreheads,</hi> nor in <hi>their Hands,</hi> that they may put on the <hi>whole Armour of God,</hi> and take to themſelves the golden <hi>Shield of Faith,</hi> with the <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 6. 16, 17. Triumphing victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly over all the legions of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let's cry to the Lord for the <hi>Country,</hi> that he would awaken the ſecure, and quicken every man to ſet his hand to the <hi>right plow without looking back,</hi> Luke 9. 62. to dreſs his own Vine and Fig-tree, that this whole Land may become the <hi>Garden of the Lord,</hi> that there may be <hi>no more plowing with an Ox and an Aſs, or ſowing our Fields with divers ſeeds, or wearing Garments of woollen and Linnen,</hi> or mingling a prophane life with profeſſion of Godlineſs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 10, 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let's cry to the Lord on the behalf of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that he would pleaſe to call them out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Revel. 18. 4. That they no longer worſhip the <hi>golden Calves of</hi> Dan <hi>and</hi> Bethel, that they may Renounce all ſubjection to the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſubmit to the holy Laws of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> who is wont to receive into the vineyard of his favour, all thoſe, whatever they have been, that come to him at the <hi>eleventh hour of the day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93566:18"/> 7. Let's cry unto the Lord on the behalf of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters,</hi> that for one tear, their Brethren drop for their own Sins or the <hi>Sins of Zion,</hi> they may drop ten, nay an hundred for one. That they may be <hi>Exceeding humble</hi> under the Honour they have been called to in carrying the Croſs of Chriſt, and in giving Teſtimony to the oppreſſed Truth of the Goſpel. That they may be gentle, and quiet under all the Scorn and Indignation of the <hi>Iſhmaelites.</hi> That they may conſtantly carry their enemies in the Arms of their Prayers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, Deſiring him to forgive and bleſs them; that their profeſſion may be Crown'd with perſeverance, that their <hi>Sackcloth</hi> may be kept clean and unſullied that they may at length arive ſafely in that holy Land, where love hath the the Throne, and reigns for ever, there can be no greater hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs deſired than to <hi>ſtand eternally before the Throne, and before the Lamb, with white robes, and with palms in our Hands,</hi> Rev. 7. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> having earneſtly deſired the Lord to give <hi>England,</hi> Repentance Let us with an equal fervour, Implore his pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, let us all ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>God be merciful to our Sin, for it is Great,</hi> Pſal. 25. 11. The grace of God teaches thoſe that are in Covenant with him to draw Arguments for mercy as well from the greatneſs of their Sin, as from the greatneſs of their miſery, knowing, that <hi>where Sin abounds, Grace delights to abound much more,</hi> Rom. 5. 20. But then becauſe God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to us, who are Sinful, we muſt not continue to be Sinful becauſe he is merciful. <hi>Englands</hi> Sin is great; God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and forgive it; when we deal with men we urge the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an offence, as a motive to Forgiveneſs, but when we have to do with God 'tis otherwiſe, <hi>God be merciful to our Sin, for it is great; Englands</hi> Sin is great, it is exceeding Sinful. Light hath ſhined among us, but we <hi>love Darkneſs;</hi> Chriſt doth not Reign, his Government is refuſed: 'Tis often ſaid in the Pulpits, and in the Prints, that the <hi>Church of England</hi> is the <hi>beſt Church</hi> in the world; O what a horrid thing is it then, if the People of <hi>England</hi> be the worſt Livers, and the greateſt Perſecutors of their Brethren in the world! Whither muſt we go to find out greater Swearing Drinking, Whoreing under a brow of Braſs than in theſe Kingdoms? Where ſuch prodigious Pride, ſtrange Apparel, general Prophaneneſs, Unthankfulneſs for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93566:18"/> unfruitfulneſs under it, and which is to be Lamented with Tears of Blood; an unaccountable ſcoffing at all ſerious Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as is to be found among our ſelves? O let's joyn moſt heartily in our humble Supplications now and at all times, that theſe Kingdoms may be waſhed all over in the Blood of the Covenant; that the deſtroying Angel may not break in upon us, which is the next thing to be ſpoken unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We ſhould wreſtle with the Lord, that he would pleaſe to Remove our Judgments, and prevent our Deſolations <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 16. <hi>I deſire not the woful day the Lord God knows,</hi> but if we turn not from our Idols, the woful day will come, I beſeech you let's ariſe, and <hi>ſtand in the Gap,</hi> by Faith, and Prayer, and Holineſs; had not <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord ſtood in <hi>the Breach,</hi> the fury of the Lord had broke in like a flood upon the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Pſal. 106. 23. with Exod. 32. 10. The Goodneſs of God had ſet up a Fence round about the Church in the Wilderneſs, but the <hi>golden Calf,</hi> which <hi>Aaron</hi> made, made a breach in that Fence, at which divine vengeance was ruſhing in, but <hi>Moſes</hi> haſtned, and ſtood in the breach, and ſaved <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſome Arguments humbly to plead before our God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe Kingdoms are Eſpouſed to the Lord, and their Name was once <hi>Hephziba</hi> and <hi>Beula,</hi> Iſa. 62. 4. <hi>The Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, O Lord leave us not, we are called by thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord as we have heard loves not <hi>putting away,</hi> Mal. 2. 16. but always Betrothes to himſelf a people in great <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> he is always firſt in making Covenants of Love, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver firſt in departing from them, if he ſhould give to our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>libellum repudii a Bill of Divorce,</hi> Iſa. 5. 1. we ſhould find it written there that our Mother had firſt play'd the Harlot with many Lovers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have a gracious Promiſe, That if a wicked Backſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people repent and return, they ſhall be received to favour, Jer. 3. 1. <hi>They ſay if a Man put away his Wife, and ſhe go from him and become another Mans, ſhall he return to her again, ſhall not that Land be greatly polluted? But thou haſt play'd the Harlot with many Lovers, yet return again to me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> O let us tell the Lord upon our Knees this day, that now, even now we will return to him, and to give an aſſurance of it, <hi>England</hi> hath put on her <hi>Garments of Mourning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93566:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> 4. The Name of the Lord is concerned in <hi>England</hi>'s Mercy, Deliverance, and Eſtabliſhment, the Eye of all <hi>Europe</hi> is fixt upon us, and waits to ſee the Iſſue of our Affairs, whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall Triumph or <hi>Antichriſt, Michael</hi> or the <hi>Dragon,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Rod of Aaron</hi> will ſwallow up the Rod of the <hi>Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or the <hi>Magicians Rod</hi> devour the <hi>Rod of Aaron;</hi> and let us ſay as <hi>Joſhuah</hi> did, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou do unto thy great Name? Joſh.</hi> 7. 9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We have had experience of the kindneſs of God to a worthleſs people, <hi>he hath delivered</hi> and <hi>doth deliver</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (Glory to his Grace for our good News out of the <hi>North)</hi> and we humbly hope he will deliver in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> too, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. He who ſaved us from <hi>Paganiſm</hi> of old, from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm</hi> of late, is able to ſave us <hi>from our ſelves;</hi> to Heal our Diviſions, to Remove our Offences, to Unite our Hearts, and to ſet up the Government and Kingdom of Chriſt in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry among us.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now conclude with this only <hi>Motive</hi> to excite us to this Duty of Prayer, upon which we have been diſcourſing, <hi>They who pray for the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall proſper,</hi> Pſal. 122. 6. <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilli, felices, ſine cruce,</hi> as he that can forgive a Brother will find God forgiving him, ſo he that can pray for the Proſperity of Church and State, will find peace ſpiringing up in his Soul, <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee,</hi> they ſhall have marks of Mercy put upon them, when the deſtroying Angels walk about the Streets with <hi>ſlaughter Weapons</hi> in their Hands, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. 2, 4. in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this with that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 7. I have only this to obſerve, that mark of mercy in <hi>Exodus</hi> was put upon the <hi>Door-poſts,</hi> to ſhew that God would then ſave by <hi>Families;</hi> but in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 'tis put on the <hi>Forehead,</hi> that we may learn from thence, that the Lord now in an evil day undertakes only for the ſafety of <hi>ſingle Perſons.</hi> My Brethren, let me prevail with you in this thing; go home, <hi>ſowin tears,</hi> you ſhall <hi>reap in joy:</hi> Be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Mourners,</hi> and not among the <hi>Sinners in Zion,</hi> ſo ſhall we be Proſperous here and Glorious hereafter. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93566:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
